<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  Copyright 2010-2011 The myBatis Team

  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at

    http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->

<!--
  version: $Id$
-->
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">

  <properties>
    <title>MyBatis Migrations | Migrate > bootstrap</title>
    <author email="mybatis-dev@googlegroups.com">The MyBatis Team</author>
  </properties>

  <body>
    <section name="The 'bootstrap' command">
      <p>If you’re working from an existing database, you need to start from a known state. There’s no point in trying
      to rewind time and shoehorn your existing database into a series of migration scripts. It’s more practical to just
      accept the current state of your database schema and identify this as the starting point. The bootstrap script and
      command exist for this reason.</p>

      <p> In the scripts directory you’ll find <code>bootstrap.sql</code>. You can put your
      existing DDLscript in this file. If you don’t have a DDL script, you can export your existing database schema and
      put it in the bootstrap file. You’ll want to clean it up so that it doesn’t contain anything specific to any one
      environment, but otherwise almost any script should work. Watch out for DDL that contains conditional elements or
      branching logic that could generate multiple schemas. While this is sometimes necessary, it’s a really good idea
      to try to eliminate this aspect of your database schema (put such conditional and branching logic in your code or
      stored procedures instead). If you have multiple DDL files, you’ll have to merge them into the single bootstrap
      file.</p>

      <p>But worry not, it’s the last time you’ll ever modify it. One of the rules above was immutable change scripts...
      the bootstrap is included in that rule.</p>

      <p><span class="label warning">Note</span> The bootstrap.sql is a plain text file and is not a valid “migration”
      that you’ll learn about later. It’s meant to be similar to the scripts you probably already use. Therefore you
      cannot rollback the bootstrap file, nor is it tracked in the audit logs... without exception, whatever you put in
      the bootstrap file cannot leverage the benefits of the other migration commands. But we have to start somewhere,
      and it’s best to look forward.</p>

      <p>To run the bootstrap file, you simply call the bootstrap command. You do this once to initialize your database
      into a known working state. From then on, you’ll use migration scripts to evolve the database schema.</p>

      <p>The bootstrap command has no parameters. So running it is as simple as:</p>

      <source>/home/cbegin/testdb$ migrate bootstrap</source>

      <p>As usual, you can use the <code>--path</code> option to specify the repository path, otherwise the current
        working directory is assumed to be the root of your migration repository (aka migration path).</p>

      <p>If there are environment specific elements in your bootstrap script, you’ll learn later that you can use
      properties to deal with those.</p>
    </section>
  </body>

</document>
